Guide to the Melville Best Anderson Papers, 1926-1930
Department of Special Collections
Anderson, Melville Best Papers,
1926-1930
M0731
Anderson, Melville Best, 1851-1933
1 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Primarily incoming correspondence to Melville Best Anderson from former students Anna Strunsky Walling and Agnes Smith Manucci Capponi, from colleagues E.O. James, David Starr Jordan, Thomas H. MacBride, Charles Eliot Norton, and Paget Toynbee (fellow Dante scholar), as well as less detailed correspondence from Fremont Older and former students Samuel S. McClure and John Huston Finley, as well as various other academic and literary figures of the early twentieth century, including many affiliated with Stanford.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Patricia Sage Liedtke, 1985.
Biography
Melville Best Anderson was born in Kalamazoo Michigan in 1851, the son of Helen Best Anderson and Edward Coffin Anderson. His father's career as a teacher and minister caused the family to move several times during Melville's childhood. At eighteen he entered Cornell University, where he began life-long friendships with other young scholars, including David Starr Jordan. In 1872 Anderson began his career as a literary scholar, and in the next decades he taught at Butler University, Knox College, Purdue University and the University of Iowa. In 1891 Anderson came to Stanford at the request of David Starr Jordan to serve as head of the English Department. Professor Anderson remained at Stanford until 1910, when he retired emeritus to devote himself to Dante scholarship. His most celebrated literary achievement was his translation of the Divina Comedia (final edition, Oxford University Press: 1932). Anderson died on June 22, 1933 at his brother's home in La Jolla, California.
Scope and Content
The Melville Best Anderson Collection of primarily incoming correspondence was donated to the Stanford Libraries by Patricia Sage Liedtke in 1985. The collection measures 1.0 linear foot in two regular-sized manuscript boxes, and consists of letters to Professor Anderson from family, friends, students and colleagues.
The collection includes extensive correspondence from former students Agnes Smith Manucci Capponi and Anna Strunsky Walling (poet and socialist), and from colleagues E. O. James, David Starr Jordan, Thomas H. MacBride, Charles Eliot Norton and Paget Toynbee (fellow Dante scholar). Also included is less detailed correspondence from Fremont Older (writer) and former students Samuel S. Mc Clure and John Huston Finley, as well as various other academic and literary figures, including many affiliated with Stanford. More materials on Melville Best Anderson are available in the Anderson Family Papers collection (M051).
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Anderson, Melville Best, 1851-1933.; Capponi, Agnes Smith Mannucci.; Capponi, Agnes Smith Manucci.; Finley, John H. (John Huston), 1863-1940.; James, E.O.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931.; MacBride, Thomas H.; McClure, S.S. (Samuel Sidney), 1857-1949.; Norton, Charles Eliot, 1827-1931.; Older, Fremont.; Toynbee, Paget Jackson, 1855-1932.; Walling, Anna Strunsky, 1879-; American literature--20th century.
Collection Contents
- Last Name Unknown (including several relatives)n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- A-American (including Raymond Alden, Evelyn Wight Allan)n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Anderson; Anderson, Edward P.1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Anderson, Melville Best1929 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  (outgoing correspondence including letters to Agnes Capponi and Livingston Farrand)
- Anderson, Rachel and Anderson, Robert Van Vleck1922-1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Andrews-Calkins (including Anna Cox Brinton)n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Capponi, Agnes(n.d., 1929) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Carter-D (including Arthur Cathcart)n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- E-Fn.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  (including Homer Earle, Livingston Farrand, John Finley)
- Gn.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- H-Heygard (including Howard Hanson)n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Hodges-Hope (including Herbert C. and Lou Henry Hoover)1913-1929 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- James, E.0.(n.d., 1924-1930) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Jordan, David Starr and Jessie Knight(1922-1929) (Box 1, Folder 14)
- K-L (including Mrs. Thomas [Elizabeth Gurnee Anderson] Lossing)1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- MacBride, Thomas H.(1914-1931) (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Markham-Morsen.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- N-Nonesuchn.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Norton, Charles Eliot(1894-1908) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  (including Dante translation by Anderson, notes by Norton)
- Older, Fremont(1928) (Box 2, Folder 2)
- P-Qn.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- R-Slatteryn.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Smith-Tnorpn.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Toynbee, Paget(1922-1930) (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Walling, Anna S.(n.d., 1924-1927) (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Walling, Anna S.(1929) (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Walling, Anna S.(Jan.-June, 1930) (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Walling, Anna S.(July-Dec., 1930) (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Wick-Yale (including Ray Lyman Wilbur)1922 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Pamphletsn.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)